Register of the Vladimir Mikhailovich Perekrestenko Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir Mikhailovich Perekrestenko papers
1951-1980
2000C112
Hoover Institution Archives
4 microfilm reels (0.6 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, personal documents, and printed matter, relating to displaced persons camps after World War II, and to Russian émigré affairs.
Perekrestenko, Vladimir Mikhailovich, 1887-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
V. M. Perekrestenko was born in Kiev on 7 July 1887. In 1915 he received his commission as an officer in the Russian army, with which he fought through the First World and Russian Civil Wars, finally evacuating to Yugoslavia.
He left Yugoslavia following the Second World War. From 1954 to 1961, he lived in Belgium, where he was secretary of the Union of Russian Writers and Journalists in Belgium (Soiuz russkikh pisatelei i zhurnalistov v Bel'gii). In 1961 he left for the United States, where he remained until his death in San Francisco.
Perekrestenko was a correspondent for numerous émigré newspapers, and his collection contains many of his writings, including the works "Lageria" and "Na pereput'i," which describe experiences in displaced persons camps. Of particular interest is the office file of the Soiuz russkikh pisatelei i zhurnalistov v Bel'gii, detailing its founding and activities up to 1961.
Chronology
1887 July 7 Born, Kiev, Russia
1915 Commissioned as an officer, Russian army
1951 Left Yugoslavia
1954-1961 Lived in Belgium Secretary of the Soiuz russkikh pisatelei i zhurnalistov v Bel'gii
1961 Emigrated to the United States
? Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
V. M. Perekrestenko was a journalist and writer who wrote primarily newspaper columns on current events for the émigré press. This collection contains drafts of these columns, as well as more substantial pieces, such as an unpublished novel entitled "Protoierei Andzhelko" and unpublished autobiographical works based on his experience in displaced persons' camps in post-World War Two Europe, entitled "Lageria" and "Na pereput'i." Also of interest is the subject file Soiuz russkikh pisatelei i zhurnalistov v Bel'gii, of which organization he was secretary.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Belgium.; Refugees.; Russia.; Russians--Belgium.; Russians--United States.; United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1951-1980 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Identity and immigration papers, letters of recommendation, military service records and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1956-1980 and undated (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings (Box 1-3)
  Articles, autobiographical writings, novels, poetry, and short stories, arranged alphabetically by title
- Subject File, 1955-1979 (Box 3)
  Clippings, correspondence, notes, and writings, arranged alphabetically by heading
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1951-1980 (Box 1)
  - Identity papers (Folder 1: 1)
  - Immigration papers (Folder 1: 2)
  - Letters of recommendation for Perekrestenko (Folder 1: 3)
  - Military service records (Folder 1: 4)
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 5)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1956-1980 and undated
  - General, 1963-1979 and undated (Folder 1: 6)
  - Unidentified, 1956-1980 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Chasovoi, undated (Folder 1: 8)
  - Pavlova, Vera, 1964-1965 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Perekrestenko, Antonina, 1979-1980 (Folder 1: 10)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - General
    - Correspondence and addresses of publishers (Folder 1: 11)
    - Newspaper columns, n.d.
      Includes associated correspondence
      - Holograph (Folder 1: 12)
      - Typescript (Folder 1: 13)
    - Poetry, n.d. (Folder 1: 14)
      Typescript
    - Short stories, n.d. (Folder 1: 15)
    - Unidentified fragments, n.d. (Folder 1: 16)
      Holograph and typescript. Includes commentary on current affairs, short stories and pieces related to larger works
  - "The District Attorney Reformer,", n.d. (Folder 1: 17)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Iz zapisok zhurnalista,", n.d. (Folder 1: 18)
  - "Lageria,", n.d. (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Na pereput'i,", n.d.
    - Background materials. (Folder 2: 2)
      Includes correspondence and documents dating from Perekresetenko's experience in displaced person camps in Europe following the Second World War
    - Holograph (fragments and drafts) (Folder 2: 3)
    - Typescript (Folder 2: 4-5)
  - "Neuviazka," Chasovoi, n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
    Printed copy
  - "Protoierei Andzhelko," (Folder 2: 7-8)
    Typescript (numerous drafts)
  - "Protoierei Andzhelko" (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Roman Romanova,", n.d. (Folder 3: 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1955-1979
  - Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco (Folder 3: 3)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov'--United States (Folder 3: 4)
  - Soiuz russkikh pisatelei i zhurnalistov v Bel'gii. (Folder 3: 5)
    Correspondence with I. P. Kaznov, K. N. Platunov, and others, founding documents, office records, writings, mainly poetry, by various authors (including I. Kaznov and V. Ingul), and printed matter
  - Miscellany (Folder 3: 6)